<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd">
<!--
  ~ Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one
  ~ or more contributor license agreements. See the NOTICE file
  ~ distributed with this work for additional information
  ~ regarding copyright ownership. The ASF licenses this file
  ~ to you under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the
  ~ "License"); you may not use this file except in compliance
  ~ with the License. You may obtain a copy of the License at
  ~
  ~ http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0
  ~
  ~ Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing,
  ~ software distributed under the License is distributed on an
  ~ "AS IS" BASIS, WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY
  ~ KIND, either express or implied. See the License for the
  ~ specific language governing permissions and limitations
  ~ under the License.
  -->
<book>
    <bookinfo>
        <title>Axiom User Guide</title>
        <releaseinfo>&version;
        </releaseinfo>

        <legalnotice>
            <para>
                Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one or more contributor license agreements. See
                the NOTICE file distributed with this work for additional information regarding copyright ownership. The
                ASF licenses this file to you under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the "License"); you may not use
                this file except in compliance with the License. You may obtain a copy of the License at
            </para>
            <para>
                <ulink url="http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0"/>
            </para>
            <para>
                Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software distributed under the License is
                distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS, WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or
                implied. See the License for the specific language governing permissions and limitations under the
                License.
            </para>
        </legalnotice>
    </bookinfo>

    <toc/>

    <chapter>
        <title>Introduction</title>
        <section>
            <title>What is Axiom?</title>
            <para>
                Axiom stands for <firstterm>Axis Object Model</firstterm> and refers to the XML infoset model
                that is initially developed for Apache Axis2. XML infoset refers to the information included inside the
                XML, and for programmatic manipulation it is convenient to have a representation of this XML infoset in
                a language specific manner. For an object oriented language the obvious choice is a model made up of
                objects. <ulink url="http://www.w3.org/DOM/">DOM</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.jdom.org/">JDOM</ulink>
                are two such XML models. Axiom is conceptually similar to such an XML model by its external behavior but
                deep down it is very much different. The objective of this tutorial is to introduce the basics of Axiom and
                explain the best practices to be followed while using Axiom. However, before diving in to the deep end of
                Axiom it is better to skim the surface and see what it is all about!
            </para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>For whom is this Tutorial?</title>
            <para>
                This tutorial can be used by anyone who is interested in Axiom and needs to
                gain a deeper knowledge about the model. However, it is assumed that the
                reader has a basic understanding of the concepts of XML (such as
                <ulink src="http://www.w3.org/TR/REC-xml-names/">Namespaces</ulink>) and a working
                knowledge of tools such as <ulink href="http://ant.apache.org/">Ant</ulink>.
                Knowledge in similar object models such as DOM will be quite helpful in
                understanding Axiom, mainly to highlight the differences and similarities
                between the two, but such knowledge is not assumed. Several links are listed
                in <xref linkend="links"/> that will help understand the basics of
                XML.
            </para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>What is Pull Parsing?</title>
            <para>
                Pull parsing is a recent trend in XML processing. The previously popular XML
                processing frameworks such as
                <ulink url="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Simple_API_for_XML">SAX</ulink> and
                <ulink url="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Document_Object_Model">DOM</ulink> were
                "push-based" which means the control of the parsing was in the hands of the
                parser itself. This approach is fine and easy to use, but it was not
                efficient in handling large XML documents since a complete memory model will
                be generated in the memory. Pull parsing inverts the control and hence the
                parser only proceeds at the users command. The user can decide to store or
                discard events generated from the parser. Axiom is based on pull parsing. To
                learn more about XML pull parsing see the
                <ulink url="http://www.bearcave.com/software/java/xml/xmlpull.html">XML pull
                parsing introduction</ulink>.
            </para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>A Bit of History</title>
            <para>
                As mentioned earlier, Axiom was initially developed as part of Axis and simply
                called <firstterm>OM</firstterm>.
                The original OM was proposed as a store for the pull parser events for
                later processing, at the Axis summit held in Colombo, Sri Lanka, in September
                2004. However, this approach was soon improved and OM was pursued as a
                complete <ulink url="http://dret.net/glossary/xmlinfoset">XML infoset</ulink> model
                due to its flexibility. Several implementation techniques were attempted
                during the initial phases. The two most promising techniques were the table
                based technique and the link list based technique. During the intermediate
                performance tests the link list based technique proved to be much more memory
                efficient for smaller and mid sized XML documents. The advantage of the table
                based OM was only visible for the large and very large XML documents, and
                hence, the link list based technique was chosen as the most suitable. Initial
                efforts were focused on implementing the XML infoset (XML Information Set)
                items which are relevant to the SOAP specification (DTD support, Processing
                Instruction support, etc were not considered). The advantage of having a
                tight integration was evident at this stage and this resulted in having SOAP
                specific interfaces as part of OM rather than a layer on top of it. OM was
                deliberately made
                <ulink url="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Application_programming_interface">API</ulink>
                centric. It allows the implementations to take place independently and
                swapped without affecting the program later.
            </para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Features of Axiom</title>
            <para>
                Axiom is a lightweight, deferred built XML infoset representation based on
                StAX (<ulink url="http://www.jcp.org/en/jsr/detail?id=173">JSR 173</ulink>), which
                is the standard streaming pull parser API. The object model can be
                manipulated as flexibly as any other object model (Such as
                <ulink url="http://www.jdom.org/">JDOM</ulink>), but underneath, the objects will be
                created only when they are absolutely required. This leads to much less
                memory intensive programming. Following is a short feature overview of OM.
            </para>
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        <emphasis role="bold">Lightweight</emphasis>: Axiom is specifically targeted to be
                        lightweight. This is achieved by reducing the depth of the hierarchy,
                        number of methods and the attributes enclosed in the objects. This makes
                        the objects less memory intensive.
                    </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        <emphasis role="bold">Deferred building</emphasis>: By far this is the most important
                        feature of Axiom. The objects are not made unless a need arises for them.
                        This passes the control of building over to the object model itself
                        rather than an external builder.
                    </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        <emphasis role="bold">Pull based</emphasis>: For a deferred building mechanism a pull
                        based parser is required. Axiom is based on
                        <ulink url="http://today.java.net/pub/a/today/2006/07/20/introduction-to-stax.html">StAX</ulink>,
                        the standard pull parser API.
                    </para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
            <important>
                <para>
                    Axiom is tightly bound to StAX API. To work with Axiom
                    a StAX compliant parser and the API <emphasis>must</emphasis> be present in the
                    classpath.
                </para>
            </important>
            <para>
                The Following image shows how Axiom API is viewed by the user
            </para>
            <figure>
                <title>Architecture overview</title>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata fileref="architecture.jpg" format="JPG"/>
                    </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
            </figure>
            <para>
                OM Builder wraps the raw xml character stream through the StAX reader API.
                Hence, the complexities of the pull event stream is transparent to the
                user.
            </para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>A Bit About Caching</title>
            <para>
                Since Axiom is a deferred built object model, It incorporates the concept of
                caching. Caching refers to the creation of the objects while parsing the pull
                stream. The reason why this is so important is because caching can be turned
                off in certain situations. If so the  parser proceeds without building the
                object structure. User can extract the raw pull stream from Axiom and use that
                instead of the object model. In this case it is sometimes beneficial to switch off
                caching. <xref linkend="advanced"/> explains
                more on accessing the raw pull stream and switching on and off the
                caching.
            </para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Where Does SOAP Come into Play?</title>
            <para>
                In a nutshell <ulink url="http://www.w3schools.com/SOAP/soap_intro.asp">SOAP</ulink> is an
                information exchange protocol based on XML. SOAP has a defined set of XML
                elements that should be used in messages. Since Axis2 is a "SOAP Engine" and
                Axiom is built for Axis2, a set of SOAP specific objects were also defined along
                with Axiom. These SOAP Objects are extensions of the general object model classes.
            </para>
        </section>
    </chapter>

    <chapter>
        <title>Working with Axiom</title>
        <section>
            <title>Obtaining the Axiom Binary</title>
            <para>
                There are several methods through which the Axiom binary can be obtained:
            </para>
            <orderedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        If your project uses Maven, then it is sufficient to add Axiom as a dependency,
                        as described in <xref linkend="using-maven2"/>. Releases are available from
                        the central repository, and snapshots are available from
                        <literal>http://repository.apache.org/snapshots/</literal>. 
                    </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        A prebuilt binary distribution can be
                        <ulink url="http://ws.apache.org/axiom/download.cgi">downloaded</ulink>
                        from the site. Source distributions are also available. They can be built
                        using Maven 2, by executing <command>mvn install</command> in the root
                        directory of the distribution.
                    </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        It is also possible to check out the source code for the current development
                        version (trunk) or previous releases from the Subversion repository and build it
                        using Maven 2. Detailed information on getting the source code
                        from the Subversion repository is found
                        <ulink url="http://ws.apache.org/axiom/source-repository.html">here</ulink>.
                    </para>
                </listitem>
            </orderedlist>
            <para>
                Once the Axiom binary is obtained by any of the above ways, it should be
                included in the classpath for any of the Axiom based programs to work.
                Subsequent sections of this guide assume that this build step is complete
                and <filename>axiom-api-&version;.jar</filename> and <filename>axiom-impl-&version;.jar</filename> are
                present in the classpath along with the StAX API jar file and a StAX
                implementation.
            </para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Creating an object model programmatically</title>
            <para>
                An object model instance can be created programmatically by instantiating the objects
                representing the individual nodes of the document and then assembling them into a
                tree structure. Axiom defines a set of interfaces representing the different node types.
                E.g. <classname>OMElement</classname> represents an element, while <classname>OMText</classname>
                represents character data that appears inside an element.
                Axiom requires that all node instances are created using a factory.
                The reason for this is to cater for different implementations of the Axiom API,
                as shown in <xref linkend="fig_api"/>.
            </para>
            <figure id="fig_api">
                <title>The Axiom API with different implementations</title>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata fileref="api.jpg" format="JPG"/>
                    </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
            </figure>
            <para>
                Two implementations are currently shipped with Axiom:
            </para>
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        The Linked List implementation (LLOM). This is the standard implementation. As the
                        name implies, it uses linked lists to store collections of nodes.
                    </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        DOOM (DOM over OM), which adds support for the DOM API.
                    </para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
            <para>
                For each implementation, there are actually three factories: one for plain XML, and the other
                ones for the two SOAP versions. The factories for the default implementation can be obtained
                by calling the appropriate static methods in <classname>OMAbstractFactory</classname>.
                E.g. <methodname>OMAbstractFactory.getOMFactory()</methodname> will return the proper
                factory for plain XML. <xref linkend="list2"/> shows how this factory is used to create
                several <classname>OMElement</classname> instances.
            </para>
            <example id="list2">
                <title>Creating an object model programmatically</title>
<programlisting>//create a factory
OMFactory factory = OMAbstractFactory.getOMFactory();
//use the factory to create two namespace objects
OMNamespace ns1 = factory.createOMNamespace("bar","x");
OMNamespace ns2 = factory.createOMNamespace("bar1","y");
//use the factory to create three elements
OMElement root = factory.createOMElement("root",ns1);
OMElement elt11 = factory.createOMElement("foo1",ns1);
OMElement elt12 = factory.createOMElement("foo2",ns1);</programlisting>
            </example>
            <para>
                The Axiom API defines several methods to assemble individual objects into a tree
                structure. The most prominent ones are the following two methods available on
                <classname>OMElement</classname> instances:
            </para>
<programlisting>public void addChild(OMNode omNode);
public void addAttribute(OMAttribute attr);</programlisting>
            <para>
                <methodname>addChild</methodname> will always add the child as the last child of the parent.
                <xref linkend="ex-addChild"/> shows how this method is used to assemble the three elements
                created in <xref linkend="list2"/> into a tree structure.
            </para>
            <example id="ex-addChild">
                <title>Usage of <methodname>addChild</methodname></title>
<programlisting>//set the children
elt11.addChild(elt21);
elt12.addChild(elt22);
root.addChild(elt11);
root.addChild(elt12);</programlisting>
            </example>
            <para>
                A given node can be removed from the tree by calling the <methodname>detach()</methodname>
                method. A node can also be removed from the tree by calling the remove
                method of the returned iterator which will also call the detach method of
                the particular node internally.
            </para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Creating an object model by parsing an XML document</title>
            <para>
                Creating an object model from an existing document involves a second concept, namely
                that of a <firstterm>builder</firstterm>. The responsibility of the builder is to
                instantiate nodes corresponding to the information items in the document being parsed.
                Note that as for programmatically created object models, this still involves the
                factory, but it is now the builder that will call the <methodname>createXxx</methodname>
                methods of the factory.
            </para>
            <para>
                There are different types of builders, corresponding to different types of
                input documents, namely: plain XML, SOAP, XOP and MTOM. The appropriate type of
                builder should be created using the corresponding static method in
                <classname>OMXMLBuilderFactory</classname>. <xref linkend="list1"/> shows the
                correct method of creating an object model for a plain XML document from an input stream.
            </para>
            <note>
                <para>
                    As explained in <xref linkend="OMXMLBuilderFactory"/>, this is the recommended way
                    of creating a builder starting with Axiom 1.2.11. In previous versions, this was done
                    by instantiating <classname>StAXOMBuilder</classname> or one of its subclasses directly.
                    This approach is still supported as well.
                </para>
            </note>
            <example id="list1">
                <title>Creating an object model from an input stream</title>
<programlisting>//create the input stream
InputStream in = new FileInputStream(file);

//create the builder
OMXMLParserWrapper builder = OMXMLBuilderFactory.createOMBuilder(in);

//get the root element
OMElement documentElement = builder.getDocumentElement();</programlisting>
            </example>
            <para>
                Several differences exist between
                a programmatically created <classname>OMNode</classname> and <classname>OMNode</classname> instances created by a builder. The most
                important difference is that the former will have no builder object enclosed,
                where as the latter always carries a reference to its builder.
            </para>
            <para>
                As stated earlier, since the object model is built as and
                when required, each and every <classname>OMNode</classname> should have a reference to its builder.
                If this information is not available, it is due to the object being created
                without a builder. This difference becomes evident when the user tries to get
                a non caching pull parser from the <classname>OMElement</classname>. This will be discussed in more
                detail in <xref linkend="advanced"/>.
            </para>
            <para>
                In order to understand the requirement of the builder reference in each
                and every <classname>OMNode</classname>, consider the following scenario. Assume that the parent
                element is built but the children elements are not. If the parent is asked to
                iterate through its children, this information is not readily available to
                the parent element and it should build its children first before attempting
                to iterate them. In order to provide a reference of the builder, each and
                every node of the object model should carry the reference to its builder. Each
                and every <classname>OMNode</classname> carries a flag that states its build status. Apart from this
                restriction there are no other constraints that keep the programmer away from
                mixing up programmatically made <classname>OMNode</classname> objects with <classname>OMNode</classname> objects built from
                builders.
            </para>
            <para>
                The SOAP object hierarchy is made in the most natural way for a
                programmer. An inspection of the API will show that it is quite close to the
                SAAJ API but with no bindings to DOM or any other model. The SOAP classes
                extend basic Axiom classes (such as the <classname>OMElement</classname>) hence, one can access a SOAP
                document either with the abstraction of SOAP or drill down to the underlying
                XML Object model with a simple casting.
            </para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Namespaces</title>
            <para>
                Namespaces are a tricky part of any XML object model and is the same in
                Axiom. However, the interface to the namespace have been made very simple.
                <classname>OMNamespace</classname> is the class that represents a namespace with intentionally
                removed setter methods. This makes the <classname>OMNamespace</classname> immutable and allows
                the underlying implementation to share the objects without any
                difficulty.
            </para>
            <para>
                Following are the important methods available in <classname>OMElement</classname> to handle
                namespaces.
            </para>
<programlisting>public OMNamespace declareNamespace(String uri, String prefix);
public OMNamespace declareNamespace(OMNamespace namespace);
public OMNamespace findNamespace(String uri, String prefix) throws OMException;</programlisting>
            <para>
                The <methodname>declareNamespaceXX</methodname> methods are fairly straightforward. Add a namespace
                to namespace declarations section. Note that a namespace declaration that has
                already being added will not be added twice. <methodname>findNamespace</methodname> is a very handy
                method to locate a namespace object higher up the object tree. It searches
                for a matching namespace in its own declarations section and jumps to the
                parent if it's not found. The search progresses up the tree until a matching
                namespace is found or the root has been reached.
            </para>
            <para>
                During the serialization a directly created namespace from the factory
                will only be added to the declarations when that prefix is encountered by the
                serializer. More of the serialization matters will be discussed in
                <xref linkend="serializer"/>.
            </para>
            <para>
                The following simple code segment shows how the namespaces are dealt in OM
            </para>
            <example id="list6">
                <title>Creating an OM document with namespaces</title>
<programlisting>OMFactory factory = OMAbstractFactory.getOMFactory();
OMNamespace ns1 = factory.createOMNamespace("bar","x");
OMElement root = factory.createOMElement("root",ns1);
OMNamespace ns2 = root.declareNamespace("bar1","y");
OMElement elt1 = factory.createOMElement("foo",ns1);
OMElement elt2 = factory.createOMElement("yuck",ns2);
OMText txt1 = factory.createOMText(elt2,"blah");
elt2.addChild(txt1);
elt1.addChild(elt2);
root.addChild(elt1);</programlisting>
            </example>
            <para>
                Serialization of the root element produces the following XML:
            </para>
<screen>&lt;x:root xmlns:x="bar" xmlns:y="bar1"&gt;&lt;x:foo&gt;&lt;y:yuck&gt;blah&lt;/y:yuck&gt;&lt;/x:foo&gt;&lt;/x:root&gt;</screen>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Traversing</title>
            <para>
                Traversing the object structure can be done in the usual way by using the
                list of children. Note however, that the child nodes are returned as an
                iterator. The Iterator supports the 'Axiom way' of accessing elements and is
                more convenient than a list for sequential access. The following code sample
                shows how the children can be accessed. The children are of the type <classname>OMNode</classname>
                that can either be <classname>OMText</classname> or <classname>OMElement</classname>.
            </para>
<programlisting>Iterator children = root.getChildren();
while(children.hasNext()){
        OMNode node = (OMNode)children.next();
}</programlisting>
            <para>
                Apart from this, every <classname>OMNode</classname> has links to its siblings. If more thorough
                navigation is needed the <methodname>getNextOMSibling()</methodname>
                and <methodname>getPreviousOMSibling()</methodname> methods can be
                used. A more selective set can be chosen by using the
                <methodname>getChildrenWithName(QName)</methodname> methods.
                The <methodname>getChildWithName(Qname)</methodname> method
                returns the first child that matches the given <classname>QName</classname> and
                <methodname>getChildrenWithName(QName)</methodname> returns a collection containing all the matching
                children. The advantage of these iterators is that they won't build the whole
                object structure at once, until its required.
            </para>
            <important>
                <para>
                    As explained in <xref linkend="iterator-changes"/>, in Axiom 1.2.10 and earlier, 
                    all iterator implementations internally stayed one
                    step ahead of their apparent location. This could have the side effect of building elements
                    that are not intended to be built at all.
                </para>
            </important>
        </section>
        <section id="serializer">
            <title>Serializer</title>
            <para>
                An Axiom tree can be serialized either as the pure object model or the pull event
                stream. The serialization uses a <classname>XMLStreamWriter</classname> object to write out the
                output and hence, the same serialization mechanism can be used to write
                different types of outputs (such as text, binary, etc.).
            </para>
            <para>
                A caching flag is provided by Axiom to control the building of the in-memory
                object model. The <classname>OMNode</classname> has two methods,
                <methodname>serializeAndConsume</methodname> and <methodname>serialize</methodname>. When
                <methodname>serializeAndConsume</methodname> is called the cache flag is reset and the serializer does
                not cache the stream. Hence, the object model will not be built if the cache
                flag is not set.
            </para>
            <para>
                The serializer serializes namespaces in the following way:
            </para>
            <orderedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        When a namespace that is in the scope but not yet declared is
                        encountered, it will then be declared.
                    </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        When a namespace that is in scope and already declared is encountered,
                        the existing declarations prefix is used.
                    </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        When the namespaces are declared explicitly using the elements
                        <methodname>declareNamespace()</methodname> method, they will be serialized even if those
                        namespaces are not used in that scope.
                    </para>
                </listitem>
            </orderedlist>
            <para>
                Because of this behavior, if a fragment of the XML is serialized, it will
                also be <emphasis>namespace qualified</emphasis> with the necessary namespace
                declarations.
            </para>
            <para>
                Here is an example that shows how to write the output to the console, with
                reference to the earlier code sample- <xref linkend="list1"/>
                that created a SOAP envelope.
            </para>
<programlisting>XMLStreamWriter writer = XMLOutputFactory.newInstance().createXMLStreamWriter(System.out);
//dump the output to console with caching
envelope.serialize(writer); 
writer.flush();</programlisting>
            <para>
                or simply
            </para>
<programlisting>System.out.println(root.toStringWithConsume());</programlisting>
            <para>
                The above mentioned features of the serializer forces a correct
                serialization even if only a part of the Axiom tree is serialized. The following
                serializations show how the serialization mechanism takes the trouble to
                accurately figure out the namespaces. The example is from <xref linkend="list6"/>
                which creates a small object model programmatically.
                Serialization of the root element produces the following:
            </para>
<screen>&lt;x:root xmlns:x="bar" xmlns:y="bar1"&gt;&lt;x:foo&gt;&lt;y:yuck&gt;blah&lt;/y:yuck&gt;&lt;/x:foo&gt;&lt;/x:root&gt;</screen>
            <para>
                However, serialization of only the foo element produces the following:
            </para>
<screen>&lt;x:foo xmlns:x="bar"&gt;&lt;y:yuck xmlns:y="bar1"&gt;blah&lt;/y:yuck&gt;&lt;/x:foo&gt;</screen>
            <para>
                Note how the serializer puts the relevant namespace declarations in place.
            </para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Complete Code for the Axiom based Document Building and Serialization</title>
            <para>
                The following code segment shows how to use Axiom for completely building
                a document and then serializing it into text pushing the output to the
                console. Only the important sections are shown here. The complete program
                listing can be found in <xref linkend="appendix"/>.
            </para>
<programlisting>//create the input stream
InputStream in = new FileInputStream(file);

//create the builder
OMXMLParserWrapper builder = OMXMLBuilderFactory.createOMBuilder(in);

//get the root element
OMElement documentElement = builder.getDocumentElement();

//dump the out put to console with caching
System.out.println(documentElement.toStringWithConsume());</programlisting>
        </section>
        <section id="StAXUtils">
            <title>Creating stream readers and writers using <classname>StAXUtils</classname></title>
            <para>
                The normal way to create <classname>XMLStreamReader</classname> and
                <classname>XMLStreamWriter</classname> instances is to first request a
                <classname>XMLInputFactory</classname> or <classname>XMLOutputFactory</classname>
                instance from the StAX API and then use the factory methods to create the
                reader or writer.
            </para>
            <para>
                Doing this every time a reader or writer is created is cumbersome and also
                introduces some overhead because on every invocation the <methodname>newInstance</methodname>
                methods in <classname>XMLInputFactory</classname> and <classname>XMLOutputFactory</classname>
                go through the process of looking up the StAX implementation to use and creating
                a new instance of the factory. The only case where this is really needed is when
                it is necessary to configure the factory in a special way (by setting properties on it).
            </para>
            <para>
                Axiom has a utility class called <classname>StAXUtils</classname> that provides
                methods to easily create readers and writers configured with default settings.
                It also keeps the created factories in a cache to improve performance. The caching
                occurs by (context) class loader and it is therefore safe to use <classname>StAXUtils</classname>
                in a runtime environment with a complex class loader hierarchy.
            </para>
            <caution>
                <para>
                    Axiom 1.2.8 implicitly assumed that <classname>XMLInputFactory</classname> and
                    <classname>XMLOutputFactory</classname> instances are thread safe. This is the case
                    for Woodstox (which is the default StAX implementation used by Axiom), but not
                    e.g. for the StAX implementation shipped with Sun's Java 6 runtime environment.
                    Therefore, when using Axiom versions prior to 1.2.9, you should avoid using <classname>StAXUtils</classname>
                    together with a StAX implementation other than Woodstox, especially in a highly
                    concurrent environment. The issue has been fixed in Axiom 1.2.9. See
                    <ulink url="https://issues.apache.org/jira/browse/WSCOMMONS-489">WSCOMMONS-489</ulink>
                    for more details.
                </para>
            </caution>
            <para>
                <classname>StAXUtils</classname> also enables a property file based configuration
                mechanism to change the default factory settings at assembly or deployment time of
                the application using Axiom. This is described in more details in
                <xref linkend="factory.properties"/>.
            </para>
            <important>
                <para>
                    The <methodname>getInputFactory</methodname> and <methodname>getOutputFactory</methodname>
                    methods in <classname>StAXUtils</classname> give access to the cached factories.
                    In versions prior to 1.2.9, Axiom didn't restrict access to the <methodname>setProperty</methodname> method
                    of these factories. In principle this makes it possible to change the configuration
                    of these factories for the whole application. However, since this depends on the
                    implementation details of <classname>StAXUtils</classname> (e.g. how factories
                    are cached) and since there is a proper configuration mechanism for that purpose,
                    using this possibility is strongly discouraged. Starting with version 1.2.9, Axiom
                    restricts access to <methodname>setProperty</methodname> to prevent tampering with
                    the cached factories.
                </para>
            </important>
            <para>
                The methods in <classname>StAXUtils</classname> to create readers and writers
                are rather self-explaining. For example to create an <classname>XMLStreamReader</classname>
                from an <classname>InputStream</classname>, use the following code:
            </para>
<programlisting>InputStream in = ...
XMLStreamReader reader = StAXUtils.createXMLStreamReader(in);</programlisting>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Releasing the parser</title>
            <para>
                As we have seen previously, when creating an object model from a stream, all nodes keep a
                reference to the builder and thus to the underlying parser. Since an XML parser instance is
                a heavyweight object, it is important to release it as soon as it is no longer required.
                The <methodname>close</methodname> method defined by the <classname>OMSerializable</classname>
                interface it used for that. Note that it doesn't matter an which node this method is
                called; it will always close and release the parser for the whole tree. The
                <varname>build</varname> parameter of the <methodname>close</methodname> method specifies
                if the node should be built before closing the parser.
            </para>
            <para>
                To illustrate this, consider <xref linkend="list1"/>. After finishing the processing of the
                object model and assuming that it will not access the object model afterwards, the code should
                be completed by the following instruction:
            </para>
<programlisting>documentElement.close(false);</programlisting>
            <para>
                Closing the parser is especially important in applications that process large numbers of
                XML documents. In addition, some StAX implementation are able to <quote>recycle</quote>
                parsers, i.e. to reset a parser instance and to reuse it on another input stream. However, this
                can only work if the parser has been closed explicitly or if the instance has been marked for
                finalization by the Java VM. Closing the parser explicitly as shown above will reduce the
                memory footprint of the application if this type of parser is used. 
            </para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Exception handling</title>
            <para>
                The fact that Axiom uses deferred building means that a call to a method in one
                of the object model classes may cause Axiom to read events from the underlying
                StAX parser, unless the node has already been built or if it was created
                programmatically. If an I/O error occurs or if the XML document being read is
                not well formed, an exception will be reported by the parser. This exception is
                propagated to the user code as an <classname>OMException</classname>.
            </para>
            <para>
                Note that <classname>OMException</classname> is an unchecked exception.
                Strictly speaking this is in violation of the principle that unchecked exceptions
                should be reserved for problems resulting from programming problems.
                There are however several compelling reasons to use unchecked exceptions in this
                case:
            </para>
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        The same API is used to work with programmatically created object models
                        and with object models created from an XML document. On a programmatically
                        created object model, an <classname>OMException</classname> in general
                        indicates a programming problem. Moreover one of the design goals of Axiom
                        is to give the user code the illusion that it is interacting with a complete
                        in-memory representation of an XML document, even if behind the scenes
                        Axiom will only create the objects on demand. Using checked exceptions
                        would break that abstraction.
                    </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        In most cases, code interacting with the object model will not be able
                        to recover from an <classname>OMException</classname>. Consider for example
                        a utility method that receives an <classname>OMElement</classname> as input
                        and that is supposed to extract some data from this information item.
                        When a parsing error occurs while iterating over the children of that
                        element, there is nothing the utility method could do to recover from this
                        error.
                    </para>
                    <para>
                        The only place where it makes sense to catch this type of exception and to
                        attempt to recover from it is in the code that creates the
                        <classname>XMLStreamReader</classname> and builder. It is clear that
                        it would not be reasonable to force developers to declare a checked exception
                        on every method that interacts with an Axiom object model only to allow
                        propagation of that exception to the code that initially created the parser.
                    </para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
            <para>
                The situation is actually quite similar to that encountered in three-tier
                applications, where the DAO layer in general wraps checked exceptions from
                the database in an unchecked exception because the business logic and the
                presentation tier will not be able to recover from these errors.
            </para>
            <para>
                When catching an <classname>OMException</classname> special attention should
                be paid if the code handling the exception again tries to access the object model.
                Indeed this will inevitably result in another exception being triggered, unless the
                code only accesses those parts of the tree that have been built successfully.
                E.g. the following code will give unexpected results because the call to
                <methodname>serializeAndConsume</methodname> will almost certainly trigger another
                exception:
            </para>
<programlisting>OMElement element = ...
try {
    ...
} catch (OMException ex) {
    ex.printStackTrace();
    element.serializeAndConsume(System.out);
}</programlisting>
            <caution>
                <para>
                    In Axiom versions prior to 1.2.8, an attempt to access the object model after
                    an exception has been reported by the underlying parser may result in an
                    <classname>OutOfMemoryError</classname> or cause Axiom to lock itself up in
                    an infinite loop. The reason for this is that in some cases, after throwing an
                    exception, the Woodstox parser (which is the default StAX implementation used
                    by Axiom) is left in an inconsistent state in which it will return an infinite
                    sequence of events. Starting with Axiom 1.2.8, the object model builder
                    will never attempt to read new events from a parser that has previously reported
                    an I/O or parsing error. These versions of Axiom are therefore safe; see
                    <ulink url="https://issues.apache.org/jira/browse/WSCOMMONS-372">WSCOMMONS-372</ulink>
                    for more details.
                </para>
            </caution>
            <note>
                <para>
                    The discussion in this section suggests that Axiom should make a
                    clear distinction between exceptions caused by parser errors and
                    exceptions caused by programming problems or other errors, e.g.
                    by using distinct subclasses of <classname>OMException</classname>.
                    This is currently not the case. This issue may be addressed in a future
                    version of Axiom.
                </para>
            </note>
        </section>
    </chapter>

    <chapter id="advanced">
        <title>Advanced Operations with Axiom</title>
        <section>
            <title>Accessing the Pull Parser</title>
            <para>
                Axiom is tightly integrated with StAX and the
                <methodname>getXMLStreamReader()</methodname> and <methodname>getXMLStreamReaderWithoutCaching()</methodname> methods in the
                <classname>OMElement</classname> provides a <classname>XMLStreamReader</classname>
                object. This <classname>XMLStreamReader</classname> instance
                has a special capability of switching between the underlying stream and the
                Axiom object tree if the cache setting is off. However, this functionality is
                completely transparent to the user. This is further explained in the
                following paragraphs.
            </para>
            <para>
                Axiom has the concept of caching, and the Axiom tree is the actual cache of the events
                fired. However, the requester can choose to get the pull events from the
                underlying stream rather than the Axiom tree. This can be achieved by getting
                the pull parser with the cache off. If the pull parser was obtained without
                switching off cache, the new events fired will be cached and the tree
                updated. This returned pull parser will switch between the object structure
                and the stream underneath, and the users need not worry about the differences
                caused by the switching. The exact pull stream the original document would
                have provided would be produced even if the Axiom tree was fully or partially
                built. The <methodname>getXMLStreamReaderWithoutCaching()</methodname> method is very useful when the
                events need to be handled in a pull based manner without any intermediate
                models. This makes such operations faster and efficient.
            </para>
            <important>
                <para>
                    For consistency reasons once the cache is
                    switched off it cannot be switched on again.
                </para>
            </important>
        </section>
    </chapter>

    <chapter>
        <title>Integrating Axiom into your project</title>
        <section id="using-maven2">
            <title>Using Axiom in a Maven 2 project</title>
            <section>
                <title>Adding Axiom as a dependency</title>
                <para>
                    If your project uses Maven 2, it is fairly easy to add Axiom to your project.
                    Simply add the following entries to the <sgmltag class="element">dependencies</sgmltag>
                    section of <filename>pom.xml</filename>:
                </para>
<programlisting><![CDATA[<dependency>
    <groupId>org.apache.ws.commons.axiom</groupId>
    <artifactId>axiom-api</artifactId>
    <version>]]>&version;<![CDATA[</version>
</dependency>
<dependency>
    <groupId>org.apache.ws.commons.axiom</groupId>
    <artifactId>axiom-impl</artifactId>
    <version>]]>&version;<![CDATA[</version>
</dependency>]]></programlisting>
                <para>
                    All Axiom releases are deployed to the Maven central repository and there is no need
                    to add an entry to the <sgmltag class="element">repositories</sgmltag> section.
                    However, if you want to work with the development (snapshot) version of Axiom, it
                    is necessary to add the Apache Snapshot Repository:
                </para>
<programlisting><![CDATA[<repository>
    <id>apache.snapshots</id>
    <name>Apache Snapshot Repository</name>
    <url>http://repository.apache.org/snapshots/</url>
    <releases>
        <enabled>false</enabled>
    </releases>
</repository>]]></programlisting>
                <tip>
                    <para>
                        If you are working on another Apache project, you don't need to add the snapshot repository
                        in the POM file since it is already declared in the <literal>org.apache:apache</literal>
                        parent POM.
                    </para>
                </tip>
            </section>
            <section>
                <title>Managing the JAF and JavaMail dependencies</title>
                <para>
                    Axiom requires the Java Activation Framework (JAF) and the JavaMail API to work. There are two
                    commonly used incarnations of these libraries: one is Sun's reference implementation, the other
                    is part of the <ulink url="http://geronimo.apache.org/">Geronimo</ulink> project. Axiom declares
                    dependencies on the Geronimo versions (though that might
                    <ulink url="https://issues.apache.org/jira/browse/WSCOMMONS-417">change</ulink> in the future).
                    If your project uses another library that depends on JAF and/or JavaMail, but that refers
                    to Sun's implementation, your project will end up with dependencies on two different
                    artifacts implementing the same API.
                </para>
                <para>
                    If you prefer Sun's implementations, then you should change the declaration of the
                    Axiom dependencies in your POM file as follow:
                </para> 
<programlisting><![CDATA[
<dependency>
    <groupId>org.apache.ws.commons.axiom</groupId>
    <artifactId>axiom-]]><replaceable>xxx</replaceable><![CDATA[</artifactId>
    <version>]]>&version;<![CDATA[</version>
    <exclusions>
        <exclusion>
            <groupId>org.apache.geronimo.specs</groupId>
            <artifactId>geronimo-activation_1.1_spec</artifactId>
        </exclusion>
        <exclusion>
            <groupId>org.apache.geronimo.specs</groupId>
            <artifactId>geronimo-javamail_1.4_spec</artifactId>
        </exclusion>
    </exclusions>
</dependency>
]]></programlisting>
                <para>
                    If you prefer Geronimo's implementation, then you need to identify the libraries
                    depending on Sun's artifacts (<literal>javax.activation:activation</literal> and
                    <literal>javax.mail:mail</literal>) and add the relevant exclusions. You can use
                    <userinput>mvn dependency:tree</userinput> to easily identify where a transitive dependency
                    comes from.
                </para>
                <para>
                    The choice between Sun's and Geronimo's implementation is to a large extend
                    a question of belief. Note however that the <literal>geronimo-javamail_1.4_spec</literal>
                    artifact used by Axiom only contains the JavaMail API, while Sun's library
                    bundles the API together with the providers for IMAP and POP3. Depending on your
                    use case that might be an advantage or disadvantage.
                </para>
            </section>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Applying application wide configuration</title>
            <para>
                Sometimes it is necessary to customize some particular aspects of Axiom for an entire
                application. There are several things that can be configured through system properties
                and/or property files. This is also important when using third party applications or
                libraries that depend on Axiom.
            </para>
            <section id="factory.properties">
                <title>Changing the default StAX factory settings</title>
                <note>
                    <para>
                        The information in this section only applies to
                        <classname>XMLStreamReader</classname> or <classname>XMLStreamWriter</classname>
                        instances created using <classname>StAXUtils</classname>
                        (see <xref linkend="StAXUtils"/>). Readers and writers created using the
                        standard StAX APIs will keep their default settings as defined by the
                        implementation (or dictated by the StAX specifications).
                    </para>
                </note>
                <note>
                    <para>
                        The feature described in this section was introduced in Axiom 1.2.9.
                    </para>
                </note>
                <para>
                    When creating a new <classname>XMLInputFactory</classname> (resp.
                    <classname>XMLInputFactory</classname>), <classname>StAXUtils</classname>
                    looks for a property file named <filename>XMLInputFactory.properties</filename>
                    (resp. <filename>XMLOutputFactory.properties</filename>) in the classpath,
                    using the same class loader as the one from which the factory is loaded
                    (by default this is the context classloader).
                    If a corresponding resource is found, the properties in that file
                    are applied to the factory using the <methodname>XMLInputFactory#setProperty</methodname>
                    (resp. <methodname>XMLOutputFactory#setProperty</methodname>) method.
                </para>
                <para>
                    This feature can be used to set factory properties of type <classname>Boolean</classname>,
                    <classname>Integer</classname> and <classname>String</classname>. The following
                    sections present some sample use cases.
                </para>
                <section>
                    <title>Changing the serialization of the CR-LF character sequence</title>
                    <para>
                        Section 2.11 of <biblioref linkend="bib.xml"/> specifies that an <quote>XML processor
                        must behave as if it normalized all line breaks in external parsed entities (including
                        the document entity) on input, before parsing, by translating both the two-character
                        sequence #xD #xA and any #xD that is not followed by #xA to a single #xA
                        character.</quote> This implies that when a Windows style line ending, i.e. a CR-LF
                        character sequence is serialized literally into an XML document, the CR character
                        will be lost during deserialization. Depending on the use case this may or may not
                        be desirable.
                    </para>
                    <para>
                        The only way to strictly preserve CR characters is to serialize them as
                        character entities, i.e. <sgmltag class="genentity">#xD</sgmltag>. This is the default
                        behavior of Woodstox. This can be easily checked using the following Java snippet:
                    </para>
<programlisting>OMFactory factory = OMAbstractFactory.getOMFactory();
OMElement element = factory.createOMElement("root", null);
element.setText("Test\r\nwith CRLF");
element.serialize(System.out);</programlisting>
                    <para>
                        This code produces the following output:
                    </para>
<screen><![CDATA[<root>Test&#xd;
with CRLF</root>]]></screen>
                    <note>
                        <para>
                            From Axiom's point of view this is actually a reasonable behavior.
                            The reason is that when creating an <classname>OMText</classname> node programmatically,
                            it is easy for the user code to normalize the text content to avoid the
                            appearance of the character entity. On the other hand, if the default
                            behavior was to serialize CR-LF literally (implying that the CR character
                            will be lost during deserialization), it would be difficult (if not
                            impossible) for user code that needs to strictly preserve the text data
                            to construct the object model in such a way as to force serialization of
                            the CR as character entity.
                        </para>
                    </note>
                    <para>
                        In some cases this behavior may be undesirable<footnote><para>See
                        <ulink url="http://jira.codehaus.org/browse/WSTX-94">WSTX-94</ulink> for a discussion
                        about this.</para></footnote>. Fortunately Woodstox allows to modify this behavior
                        by changing the value of the <varname>com.ctc.wstx.outputEscapeCr</varname> property
                        on the <classname>XMLOutputFactory</classname>. If Axiom is used (and in particular
                        <classname>StAXUtils</classname>) than this can be achieved by adding
                        a <filename>XMLOutputFactory.properties</filename> file with the following content
                        to the classpath (in the default package):
                    </para>
<programlisting>com.ctc.wstx.outputEscapeCr=false</programlisting>
                    <para>
                        Now the output of the Java snippet shown above will be:
                    </para>
<screen><![CDATA[<root>Test
with CRLF</root>]]></screen>
                </section>
                <section>
                    <title>Preserving CDATA sections during parsing</title>
                    <para>
                        By default, <classname>StAXUtils</classname> creates StAX parsers in coaelescing mode.
                        In this mode, the parser will never return two character data events in sequence, while
                        in non coaelescing mode, the parser is allowed to break up character data into smaller
                        chunks and to return multiple consecutive character events, which may improve throughput
                        for documents containing large text nodes.
                        It should be noted that <classname>StAXUtils</classname> overrides the default settings
                        mandated by the StAX specification, which specifies that by default, a StAX parser must
                        be in non coalescing mode. The primary reason is compatibility: older versions of
                        Woodstox had coalescing switched on by default.
                    </para>
                    <para>
                        A side effect of the default settings chosen by Axiom is that by default, CDATA sections
                        are not reported by parser created by
                        <classname>StAXUtils</classname>. The reason is that in coalescing mode, the parser will
                        not only coaelsce adjacent text nodes, but also CDATA sections. Applications that require
                        correct reporting of CDATA sections should therefore disable coalescing. This can be
                        achieved by creating a <filename>XMLInputFactory.properties</filename> file with the
                        following content:
                    </para>
<programlisting>javax.xml.stream.isCoalescing=false</programlisting>
                </section>
            </section>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Migrating from older Axiom versions</title>
            <para>
                This section provides information about changes in Axiom that might impact existing
                code when migrating from an older version of Axiom. Note that this section is not
                meant as a change log that lists all changes or new features. Also, before upgrading
                to a newer Axiom version, you should always check if your code uses methods or classes
                that have been deprecated. You should fix all deprecation warnings before changing the
                Axiom version. In general the Javadoc of the deprecated class or method gives you
                a hint on how to change your code.
            </para>
            <section>
                <title>Changes in Axiom 1.2.9</title>
                <section>
                    <title>System properties used by <classname>OMAbstractFactory</classname></title>
                    <para>
                        Prior to Axiom 1.2.9, <classname>OMAbstractFactory</classname> used system properties
                        as defined in the following table to determine the factory implementations to use:
                    </para>
                    <segmentedlist>
                        <?dbhtml list-presentation="table"?>
                        <segtitle>Object model</segtitle>
                        <segtitle>Method</segtitle>
                        <segtitle>System property</segtitle>
                        <segtitle>Default</segtitle>
                        <seglistitem>
                            <seg>Plain XML</seg>
                            <seg><methodname>getOMFactory()</methodname></seg>
                            <seg><varname>om.factory</varname></seg>
                            <seg><literal>org.apache.axiom.om.impl.llom.factory.OMLinkedListImplFactory</literal></seg>
                        </seglistitem>
                        <seglistitem>
                            <seg>SOAP 1.1</seg>
                            <seg><methodname>getSOAP11Factory()</methodname></seg>
                            <seg><varname>soap11.factory</varname></seg>
                            <seg><literal>org.apache.axiom.soap.impl.llom.soap11.SOAP11Factory</literal></seg>
                        </seglistitem>
                        <seglistitem>
                            <seg>SOAP 1.2</seg>
                            <seg><methodname>getSOAP12Factory()</methodname></seg>
                            <seg><varname>soap12.factory</varname></seg>
                            <seg><literal>org.apache.axiom.soap.impl.llom.soap12.SOAP12Factory</literal></seg>
                        </seglistitem>
                    </segmentedlist>
                    <para>
                        This in principle allowed to mix default factory implementations from different implementations
                        of the Axiom API (e.g. an OMFactory from the LLOM implementation and SOAP factories from DOOM).
                        This however doesn't make sense. The system properties as described above are no longer
                        supported in 1.2.9 and the default Axiom implementation is chosen using the new
                        <varname>org.apache.axiom.om.OMMetaFactory</varname> system property. For LLOM, you should set:
                    </para>
<programlisting>org.apache.axiom.om.OMMetaFactory=org.apache.axiom.om.impl.llom.factory.OMLinkedListMetaFactory</programlisting>
                    <para>
                        This is the default and is equivalent to the defaults in 1.2.8. For DOOM, you should set:
                    </para>
<programlisting>org.apache.axiom.om.OMMetaFactory=org.apache.axiom.om.impl.dom.factory.OMDOMMetaFactory</programlisting>
                </section>
                <section>
                    <title>Factories returned by <classname>StAXUtils</classname></title>
                    <para>
                        In versions prior to 1.2.9, the <classname>XMLInputFactory</classname> and
                        <classname>XMLOutputFactory</classname> instances returned by <classname>StAXUtils</classname>
                        were mutable, i.e. it was possible to change the properties of these factories. This is obviously
                        an issue since the factory instances are cached and can be shared among several thread.
                        To avoid programming errors, starting from 1.2.9, the factories are immutable and any attempt to
                        change their state will result in an <classname>IllegalStateException</classname>.
                    </para>
                    <para>
                        Note that the possibility to change the properties of these factories could be used to apply
                        application wide settings. Starting with 1.2.9, Axiom has a proper mechanism to allow this.
                        This feature is described in <xref linkend="factory.properties"/>.
                    </para>
                </section>
                <section>
                    <title>Changes in XOP/MTOM handling</title>
                    <para>
                        In Axiom 1.2.8, <classname>XMLStreamReader</classname> instances provided by Axiom could
                        belong to one of three different categories:
                    </para>
                    <orderedlist>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>
                                <classname>XMLStreamReader</classname> instances delivering plain XML.
                            </para>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>
                                <classname>XMLStreamReader</classname> instances delivering plain XML and
                                implementing a custom extension to retrieve optimized binary data.
                            </para>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>
                                <classname>XMLStreamReader</classname> instances representing XOP
                                encoded data.
                            </para>
                        </listitem>
                    </orderedlist>
                    <para>
                        As explained in <ulink url="https://issues.apache.org/jira/browse/WSCOMMONS-485">WSCOMMONS-485</ulink>
                        and <ulink url="https://issues.apache.org/jira/browse/WSCOMMONS-488">WSCOMMONS-488</ulink>,
                        in Axiom 1.2.8, the type of stream reader provided by the API was not always well defined.
                        Sometimes the type of the stream reader even depended on the state of the Axiom tree
                        (i.e. whether some part of it has been accessed or not).
                    </para>
                    <para>
                        In release 1.2.9 the behavior of Axiom was changed such that it never delivers XOP
                        encoded data unless explicitly requested to do so. By default, any <classname>XMLStreamReader</classname>
                        provided by Axiom now represents plain XML data and optionally implements the
                        <classname>DataHandlerReader</classname> extension to retrieve optimized
                        binary data. An XOP encoded stream can be requested from the <methodname>getXOPEncodedStream</methodname>
                        method in <classname>XOPUtils</classname>.
                    </para>
                </section>
            </section>
            <section id="changes-1.2.11">
                <title>Changes in Axiom 1.2.11</title>
                <section id="OMXMLBuilderFactory">
                    <title>Resurrection of the <classname>OMXMLBuilderFactory</classname> API</title>
                    <para>
                        Historically, <classname>org.apache.axiom.om.impl.llom.factory.OMXMLBuilderFactory</classname> was used to
                        create Axiom trees from XML documents. Unfortunately, this class is located in the wrong package and JAR
                        (it is implementation independent but belongs to LLOM). In Axiom 1.2.10, the standard way to create an Axiom tree
                        was therefore to instantiate <classname>StAXOMBuilder</classname> or one of its subclasses directly. However, this
                        is not optimal for two reasons:
                    </para>
                    <itemizedlist>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>
                                It relies on the assumption that every implementation of the Axiom API necessarily uses
                                <classname>StAXOMBuilder</classname>. This means that an implementation doesn't have the freedom to
                                provide its own builder implementation (e.g. in order to implement some special optimizations).
                            </para>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>
                                <classname>StAXOMBuilder</classname> and its subclasses belong to packages which have
                                <literal>impl</literal> in their names. This tends to blur the distinction between the public
                                API and internal implementation classes.
                            </para>
                        </listitem>
                    </itemizedlist>
                    <para>
                        Therefore, in Axiom 1.2.11, a new abstract API for creating builder instances was introduced.
                        It is again called <classname>OMXMLBuilderFactory</classname>, but located in the
                        <package>org.apache.axiom.om</package> package. The methods defined by this new API are similar
                        to the ones in the original (now deprecated) <classname>OMXMLBuilderFactory</classname>, so that
                        migration should be easy.
                    </para>
                </section>
                <section id="iterator-changes">
                    <title>Changes in the behavior of certain iterators</title>
                    <para>
                        In Axiom 1.2.10 and previous versions, iterators returned by methods such as <methodname>OMIterator#getChildren()</methodname>
                        internally stayed one step ahead of the node returned by the <methodname>next()</methodname> method.
                        This meant that sometimes, using such an iterator had the side effect of building elements that
                        were not intended to be built.
                        In Axiom 1.2.11 this behavior was changed such that <methodname>next()</methodname> no longer builds the nodes
                        it returns. In a few cases, this change may cause issues in existing code. One known instance
                        is the following construct (which was used internally by Axiom itself):
                    </para>
<programlisting>while (children.hasNext()) { 
    OMNodeEx omNode = (OMNodeEx) children.next(); 
    omNode.internalSerializeAndConsume(writer); 
}</programlisting>
                    <para>
                        One would expect that the effect of this code is to consume the child nodes. However, in Axiom 1.2.10 this
                        is not the case because <methodname>next()</methodname> actually builds the node.
                        Note that the code actually doesn't make sense because once a child node has been consumed, it is
                        no longer possible to retrieve the next sibling. Since in Axiom 1.2.11 the call to <methodname>next()</methodname>
                        no longer builds the child node, this code will indeed trigger an exception.
                    </para>
                    <para>
                        Another example is the following piece of code which removes all child elements with a given name:
                    </para>
<programlisting>Iterator iterator = element.getChildrenWithName(qname);
while (iterator.hasNext()) {
    OMElement child = (OMElement)iterator.next();
    child.detach();
}</programlisting>
                    <para>
                        In Axiom 1.2.10 this works as expected. Indeed, since the iterator stays one node ahead, the current
                        node can be safely removed using the <methodname>detach()</methodname> method.
                        In Axiom 1.2.11, this is no longer the case and the following code (which also works
                        with previous versions) should be used instead:
                    </para>
<programlisting>Iterator iterator = element.getChildrenWithName(qname);
while (iterator.hasNext()) {
    iterator.next();
    iterator.remove();
}</programlisting>
                    <para>
                        Note that this is actually compatible with the behavior of the Java 2 collection framework, where
                        a <classname>ConcurrentModificationException</classname> may be thrown if a thread modifies a
                        collection directly while it is iterating over the collection with an iterator.
                    </para>
                </section>
            </section>
        </section>
    </chapter>

    <chapter>
        <title>Common mistakes, problems and anti-patterns</title>
        <para>
            This chapter presents some of the common mistakes and problems people face when writing code
            using Axiom, as well as anti-patterns that should be avoided.
        </para>
        <section>
            <title>Violating the <classname>javax.activation.DataSource</classname> contract</title>
            <para>
                When working with binary (base64) content, it is sometimes necessary to write a
                custom <classname>DataSource</classname> implementation to wrap binary data that is
                available in a different form (and for which Axiom or the Java Activation Framework
                has no out-of-the-box data source implementation). Data sources are also sometimes
                (but less frequently) used in conjunction with <classname>OMSourcedElement</classname>
                and <classname>OMDataSource</classname>.
            </para>
            <para>
                The documentation of the <classname>DataSource</classname> is very clear on the expected
                behavior of the <methodname>getInputStream</methodname> method:
            </para>
<programlisting>/**
 * This method returns an InputStream representing
 * the data and throws the appropriate exception if it can
 * not do so. Note that a new InputStream object must be
 * returned each time this method is called, and the stream must be
 * positioned at the beginning of the data.
 *
 * @return an InputStream
 */
public InputStream getInputStream() throws IOException;</programlisting>
            <para>
                A common mistake is to implement the data source in a way that makes
                <methodname>getInputStream</methodname> <quote>destructive</quote>. Consider
                the implementation shown in <xref linkend="InputStreamDataSource"/><footnote><para>The example
                shown is actually a simplified version of code that is 
                <ulink url="http://svn.apache.org/repos/asf/webservices/axis2/tags/java/v1.5/modules/kernel/src/org/apache/axis2/builder/unknowncontent/InputStreamDataSource.java">part of Axis2 1.5</ulink>.</para></footnote>.
                It is clear that this data source can only be read once and that any subsequent call to
                <methodname>getInputStream</methodname> will return an already closed input stream.
            </para>
            <example id="InputStreamDataSource">
                <title><classname>DataSource</classname> implementation that violates the interface contract</title>
<programlisting>public class InputStreamDataSource implements DataSource {
    private final InputStream is;

    public InputStreamDataSource(InputStream is) {
        this.is = is;
    }

    public String getContentType() {
        return "application/octet-stream";
    }

    public InputStream getInputStream() throws IOException {
        return is;
    }

    public String getName() {
        return null;
    }

    public OutputStream getOutputStream() throws IOException {
        throw new UnsupportedOperationException();
    }
}</programlisting>
            </example>
            <para>
                What makes this mistake so vicious is that very likely it will not cause
                problems immediately. The reason is that Axiom is optimized to read the data
                only when necessary, which in most cases means only once! However, in some cases
                it is unavoidable to read the data several times. When that happens, the broken
                <classname>DataSource</classname> implementation will cause problems that may
                be extremely hard to debug.
            </para>
            <para>
                Imagine for example<footnote><para>For another example, see
                <ulink url="http://markmail.org/thread/omx7umk5fnpb6dnc"/>.</para></footnote>
                that the implementation shown above is used to produce an
                MTOM message. At first this will work without any problems because the data
                source is read only once when serializing the message. If later on the MTOM
                threshold feature is enabled, the broken implementation will (in the worst case)
                cause the corresponding MIME parts to be empty or (in the best case) trigger an
                I/O error because Axiom attempts to read from an already closed stream.
                The reason for this is that when an MTOM threshold is set, Axiom reads the data
                source twice: once to determine if its size exceeds the
                threshold<footnote><para>To do this, Axiom doesn't read the entire data source,
                but only reads up to the threshold.</para></footnote> and once during
                serialization of the message.
            </para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Issues that <quote>magically</quote> disappear</title>
            <para>
                Quite frequently users post messages on the Axiom related mailing lists about
                issues that seem to disappear by <quote>magic</quote> when they try to debug
                them. The reason why this can happen is simple. As explained earlier, Axiom uses
                deferred building, but at the same time does its best to hide that from the user,
                so that he doesn't need to worry about whether the object model has already been
                built or not. On the other hand, when serializing the object model to XML or when
                requesting a pull parser (<classname>XMLStreamReader</classname>) from a node,
                the code paths taken may be radically different depending on whether or not
                the corresponding part of the tree has already been built. This is especially
                true when caching is disabled.
            </para>
            <para>
                While the end result should be the same in all cases, it is also clear that
                in some circumstances an issue that occurs with an incompletely built tree may
                disappear if there is something that causes Axiom to build the rest of the object
                model. What is important to understand is that the <quote>something</quote> may
                be as trivial as a call to the <methodname>toString</methodname> method of an
                <classname>OMNode</classname>! The fact that adding
                <methodname>System.out.println</methodname> statements or logging instructions
                is a common debugging technique then explains why issues sometimes seem to
                <quote>magically</quote> disappear during debugging.
            </para>
            <para>
                Finally, it should be noted that inspecting an <classname>OMNode</classname>
                in a debugger also causes a call to the <methodname>toString</methodname>
                method on that object. This means that by just clicking on something in the
                <quote>Variables</quote> window of your debugger, you may completely change the
                state of the process that is being debugged!
            </para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>The OM-inside-OMDataSource anti-pattern</title>
            <section>
                <title>Weak version</title>
                <para>
                    <classname>OMDataSource</classname> objects are used in conjunction with
                    <classname>OMSourcedElement</classname> to build Axiom object model instances
                    that contain information items that are represented using a framework or API
                    other than Axiom. Wrapping this <quote>foreign</quote> data in an
                    <classname>OMDataSource</classname> and adding it to the Axiom object model
                    using an <classname>OMSourcedElement</classname> in most cases avoids the
                    conversion of the data to the <quote>native</quote> Axiom object
                    model<footnote><para>An exception is when code tries to access the children
                    of the <classname>OMSourcedElement</classname>. In this case, the
                    <classname>OMSourcedElement</classname> will be <firstterm>expanded</firstterm>,
                    i.e. the data will be converted to the native Axiom object model.</para></footnote>. 
                    The <classname>OMDataSource</classname> contract requires the implementation
                    to support two different ways of providing the data, both relying on StAX:
                </para>
                <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            The implementation must be able to provide a pull parser
                            (<classname>XMLStreamReader</classname>) from which the infoset can be
                            read.
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            The data source must be able to serialize the infoset to an
                            <classname>XMLStreamWriter</classname> (push).
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
                <para>
                    For the consumer of an event based representation of an XML infoset, it is in
                    general easier to work in pull mode. That is the reason why StAX has gained
                    popularity over push based approaches such as SAX. On the other hand for a producer
                    such as an <classname>OMDataSource</classname> implementation, it's exactly the
                    other way round: it is far easier to serialize an infoset to an
                    <classname>XMLStreamWriter</classname> (push) than to build an
                    <classname>XMLStreamReader</classname> from which a consumer can read (pull) events.
                </para>
                <para>
                    Experience indeed shows that the most challenging part in creating an
                    <classname>OMDataSource</classname> implementation is to write the
                    <methodname>getReader</methodname> method. To avoid that difficulty some
                    implementations simply build an Axiom tree and return the
                    <classname>XMLStreamReader</classname> provided by
                    <methodname>OMElement#getXMLStreamReader()</methodname>. For example, some ADB
                    (Axis2 Data Binding) versions use the following code<footnote><para>For the complete
                    code, see <ulink url="http://svn.apache.org/repos/asf/webservices/axis2/tags/java/v1.5/modules/adb/src/org/apache/axis2/databinding/ADBDataSource.java"/>.</para></footnote>:
                </para>
                <example id="adb-getReader">
                    <title><methodname>OMDataSource#getReader()</methodname> implementation used by ADB</title>
<programlisting>public XMLStreamReader getReader() throws XMLStreamException {
    MTOMAwareOMBuilder mtomAwareOMBuilder = new MTOMAwareOMBuilder();
    serialize(mtomAwareOMBuilder);
    return mtomAwareOMBuilder.getOMElement().getXMLStreamReader();
}</programlisting>
                </example>
                <para>
                    The <classname>MTOMAwareOMBuilder</classname> class referenced by this code is a special
                    implementation of <classname>XMLStreamWriter</classname> that builds an Axiom tree from the
                    sequence of events send to it. The code than uses this Axiom tree to get the
                    <classname>XMLStreamReader</classname> implementation. While this is a functionally correct
                    implementation of the <methodname>getReader</methodname> method, it is not a good
                    solution from a performance perspective and also contradicts some of the ideas on
                    which Axiom is based, namely that the object model should only be built when necessary.
                </para>
                <para>
                    Indeed, it should not be necessary to build an intermediary tree when requesting a pull
                    parser from the <classname>OMDataSource</classname> because all the required information
                    is already present in the ADB beans. Worse, if the <classname>OMSourcedElement</classname>
                    is expanded, the object model instance will be built twice: once by the
                    <methodname>getReader</methodname> and once by Axiom itself!
                </para>
                <para>
                    While constructing an Axiom tree inside the <methodname>getReader</methodname> method is clearly
                    an anti-pattern, at least in the case of ADB it is not as bad as it seems at first glance.
                    The reason is that in the case which is the most relevant for performance
                    (which is sending a Web Service response prepared using ADB), Axiom will only invoke
                    the <methodname>serialize</methodname> method and not make use of
                    <methodname>getReader</methodname>.
                </para>
                <note>
                    <para>
                        At the time of writing there is no general solution available to avoid the
                        weak version of the OM-inside-OMDataSource anti-pattern in cases where it would be far
                        too difficult to build a proper <classname>XMLStreamReader</classname>
                        implementation. Future versions of Axiom may implement a solution that
                        avoids the complexity of implementing <classname>XMLStreamReader</classname>
                        without too much performance trade-offs.
                    </para>
                </note>
            </section>
            <section>
                <title>Strong version</title>
                <para>
                    There is also a stronger version of the anti-pattern which consists in
                    implementing the <methodname>serialize</methodname> method by building an Axiom tree
                    and then serializing the tree to the <classname>XMLStreamWriter</classname>.
                    Except for very special cases, there is <emphasis role="strong">no valid reason
                    whatsoever</emphasis> to do this! To see why this is so, consider the two
                    possible cases:
                </para>
                <orderedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            The <classname>OMDataSource</classname> already implements the
                            <methodname>getReader</methodname> method in a proper way, i.e. without
                            building an intermediary Axiom tree. To properly implement
                            <methodname>serialize</methodname>, it is then sufficient
                            to pull the events from the reader returned by a call to
                            <methodname>getReader</methodname> and copy them to the
                            <classname>XMLStreamReader</classname>. The easiest and most efficient
                            way to do this is using <classname>StreamingOMSerializer</classname>:
                        </para>
                        <example id="OMDataSource-serialize">
                            <title>Proper implementation of the <methodname>OMDataSource#serialize</methodname> method</title>
<programlisting>public void serialize(XMLStreamWriter xmlWriter) throws XMLStreamException {
    StreamingOMSerializer serializer = new StreamingOMSerializer();
    serializer.serialize(getReader(), xmlWriter);
}</programlisting>
                        </example>
                        <para>
                            There is thus no need to build an intermediary object model in this case.
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            The <methodname>getReader</methodname> method also uses an intermediary
                            Axiom tree<footnote><para>See e.g.
                            <ulink url="http://svn.apache.org/repos/asf/webservices/axis2/tags/java/v1.5/modules/kernel/src/org/apache/axis2/builder/unknowncontent/UnknownContentOMDataSource.java"/>.</para></footnote>.
                            In that case it doesn't make sense to use an <classname>OMSourcedElement</classname>
                            in the first place! At least it doesn't make sense if one assumes that
                            in general the <classname>OMSourcedElement</classname> will either be
                            serialized or its content accessed after being added to the tree. Indeed,
                            in this case the Axiom tree will be built at least once (if not multiple times),
                            so that the code might as well use a normal <classname>OMElement</classname>.
                        </para>
                        <para>
                            This only leaves the very special case where the <classname>OMSourcedElement</classname>
                            is in general neither accessed nor serialized, either because it will usually be somehow
                            discarded or because the code uses <methodname>OMDataSourceExt#getObject()</methodname>
                            to retrieve the raw data. Even in that case one can argue that in general
                            it should not be too hard to implement at least the <methodname>serialize</methodname>
                            method properly by transforming the raw or foreign data directly to StAX events written to the
                            <classname>XMLStreamWriter</classname>.
                        </para>
                        <note>
                            <para>
                                Implementing the <methodname>serialize</methodname> method to serialize
                                directly to an <classname>XMLStreamWriter</classname>
                                instead of using an intermediary Axiom tree of course still leaves the question about
                                the <methodname>getReader</methodname> method open.
                                Since we are assuming that implementing <methodname>getReader</methodname>
                                properly would be too complex (otherwise one could use the code shown in
                                <xref linkend="OMDataSource-serialize"/> to avoid the
                                OM-inside-OMDataSource anti-pattern entirely), one is forced to
                                use the code shown in <xref linkend="adb-getReader"/> (and thus the weaker version of
                                the anti-pattern). However this code depends on the <classname>MTOMAwareOMBuilder</classname>
                                class which is part of <literal>axis2-adb</literal>. In some cases, depending on
                                that library may not be an option. Therefore this class should probably
                                be moved to Axiom.
                            </para>
                        </note>
                    </listitem>
                </orderedlist>
                <para>
                    QED
                </para>
            </section>
        </section>
    </chapter>

    <chapter id="appendix">
        <title>Appendix</title>
        <section>
            <title>Program Listing for Build and Serialize</title>
<programlisting>import org.apache.axiom.om.OMElement;
import org.apache.axiom.om.OMXMLBuilderFactory;
import org.apache.axiom.om.OMXMLParserWrapper;

import javax.xml.stream.XMLStreamException;
import java.io.FileInputStream;
import java.io.FileNotFoundException;
import java.io.InputStream;

public class TestOMBuilder {

    /**
     * Pass the file name as an argument
     * @param args
     */
    public static void main(String[] args) {
        try {
            //create the input stream
            InputStream in = new FileInputStream(args[0]);
            //create the builder
            OMXMLParserWrapper builder = OMXMLBuilderFactory.createOMBuilder(in);
            //get the root element
            OMElement documentElement = builder.getDocumentElement();

            //dump the out put to console with caching
            System.out.println(documentElement.toStringWithConsume()); 

        } catch (XMLStreamException e) {
            e.printStackTrace();
        } catch (FileNotFoundException e) {
            e.printStackTrace();
        }
    }
}</programlisting>
        </section>
        <section id="links">
            <title>Links</title>
            <para>
                For basics in XML
            </para>
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        <ulink url="http://www-128.ibm.com/developerworks/xml/newto/index.html">Developerworks Introduction to XML</ulink>
                    </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        <ulink url="http://www.bearcave.com/software/java/xml/xmlpull.html">Introduction to Pull parsing</ulink>
                    </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        <ulink url="http://today.java.net/pub/a/today/2006/07/20/introduction-to-stax.html">Introduction to StAX</ulink>
                    </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        <ulink url="http://www.jaxmag.com/itr/online_artikel/psecom,id,726,nodeid,147.html">Fast and Lightweight Object Model for XML</ulink>
                    </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        <ulink url="http://www-128.ibm.com/developerworks/library/x-axiom/">Get the most out of XML processing with AXIOM</ulink>
                    </para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
        </section>
    </chapter>

    <bibliography>
        <title>References</title>
        <bibliodiv>
            <title>Specifications</title>
            <biblioentry id="bib.xml">
                <abbrev>XML</abbrev>
                <title><ulink url="http://www.w3.org/TR/2008/REC-xml-20081126/">Extensible Markup Language (XML) 1.0 (Fifth Edition)</ulink></title>
                <publishername>W3C Recommendation</publishername>
                <pubdate>26 November 2008</pubdate>
            </biblioentry>
        </bibliodiv>
    </bibliography>
</book>
